How much do you need to know about a person
إلى أي مدى أنت بحاجة لمعرفة الشخص
before you'd feel comfortable making a loan?
قبل شعورك بالراحة والاطمئنان للموافقة على تقديم قرض له؟
Suppose you wanted to lend 1,000 dollars
لنفترض أنك تريد أن تقرض ١٠٠٠ دولار
to the person sitting two rows behind you.
إلى الشخص الذي يجلس خلفك على بعد صفين.
What would you need to know about that person
ما الذي تحتاج إلى معرفته عن هذا الشخص
before you'd feel comfortable?
قبل شعورك بالراحة والاطمئنان؟
My mom came to the US from India in her late thirties.
جاءت والدتي إلى الولايات المتحدة من الهند في أواخر الثلاثينات من عمرها.
She's a doctor in Brooklyn,
وهي طبيبة في مدينة "بروكلين"،
and she often lets friends and neighbors come to see her for health services,
وقالت انها كثيراً ما تسمح للأصدقاء والجيران بالمجيء لطلب الخدمات الصحية،
whether they can pay right away or not.
سواءاً أمكنهم الدفع على الفور أم لا.
I remember running into her patients with her at the grocery store
أتذكر لقاء والدتي مع مرضاها في البقالة
or on the sidewalk,
أو على رصيف المشاة،
and sometimes they would come and pay her right on the spot
وفي بعض الأحيان يقوموا بالدفع لها على الفور
for previous appointments.
أجرة مواعيد سابقة.
She would thank them,
كانت تشكرهم،
and ask them about their families and their health.
وتسألهم عن حال عائلاتهم وأحوالهم الصحية.
She gave them credit because she trusted them.
قامت بإقراضهم لأنها تثق بهم.
Most of us are like my mom.
ومعظمنا على حال والدتي.
We would give credit to someone we know
نقوم بإقراض شخص نعرفه
or that we live next to.
أو شخص نسكن بالقرب منه.
But most of us are probably not going to lend to a stranger
ولكن معظمنا لن يقوم بإقراض أشخاص مجهولين
unless we know a little something about them.
حتى نعرف شيئاً عنهم.
Banks, credit card companies and other financial institutions
البنوك وشركات بطاقات الائتمان والمؤسسات المالية الأخرى
don't know us on a personal level,
لا تعرفنا معرفة شخصية،
but they do have a way of trusting us,
ولكن لديهم طريقة للوثوق بنا،
and that's through our credit scores.
وهي من خلال نقاط الأهلية الائتمانية.
Our credit scores have been created
حيث يتم اصدار نقاط الأهلية الائتمانية
through an aggregation and analysis of our public consumer credit data.
من خلال تجميع وتحليل بيانات الائتمان الاستهلاكية العامة الخاصة بنا.
And because of them, we have pretty much easy access
وبسببها لدينا والى حد كبير سهولة الوصول
to all of the goods and services that we need,
لجميع السلع والخدمات التي نحتاجها،
from getting electricity to buying a home,
من الحصول على الكهرباء لشراء منزل،
or taking a risk and starting a business.
أو المخاطرة وبدء عمل تجاري.
But ...
لكن ...
there are 2.5 billion people around the world
هناك ٢.٥ مليار شخص حول العالم
that don't have a credit score.
لا يملكون نقاط الأهلية الائتمانية.
That's a third of the world's population.
أي ثلث سكان العالم.
They don't have a score
لا يملكون الأهلية
because there are no formal public records on them --
لعدم وجود سجلات رسمية وعامة عن سلوكهم الاستهلاكي
no bank accounts,
ولا حسابات مصرفية،
no credit histories
ولا سجلات ائتمانية
and no social security numbers.
ولا أرقام ضمان اجتماعي.
And because they don't have a score,
ولأنهم لا يمتلكون الأهلية الائتمانية
they don't have access to the credit or financial products
ليس لديهم إمكانية الوصول إلى المنتجات الائتمانية أو المالية
that can improve their lives.
والتي يمكن أن تحسن من مستوى حياتهم.
They are not trusted.
لأنهم غير موثوق بهم.
So we wanted to find a way to build trust
لذلك أردنا أن نجد طريقة لبناء الثقة
and to open up financial access for these 2.5 billion.
ولإتاحة الخدمات الائتمانية أو المالية لهذه الفئة والتي يبلغ عددها ٢.٥ مليارشخص
So we created a mobile application
فقمنا بإنشاء تطبيق على الجوال
that builds credit scores for them using mobile data.
والذي يقوم على إنشاء نقاط الأهلية الائتمانية من خلال بيانات هواتفهم،
There are currently over one billion smartphones in emerging markets.
ويوجد حالياً أكثر من مليار هاتف ذكي في الأسواق الناشئة.
And people are using them the same way that we do.
ويتم استخدام الأجهزة بنفس الطريقة التي نقوم نحن باستخدامها.
They're texting their friends, they're looking up directions,
حيث يرسلون الرسائل النصية لأصدقائهم، ويبحثون عن الاتجاهات،
they're browsing the Internet
يتصفحون مواقع الإنترنت
and they're even making financial transactions.
ويقومون حتى بإجراء المعاملات المالية.
Over time, this data is getting captured on our phones,
مع مرور الوقت، يتم الحصول على البيانات من هواتفنا،
and it provides a really rich picture of a person's life.
وتقدم صورة غنية عن حياة الأشخاص.
Our customers give us access to this data
يقوم المستهلكون بإعطائنا حق كشف البيانات
and we capture it through our mobile application.
ونقوم بجمعها من خلال البرنامج.
It helps us understand the creditworthiness
تساعدنا البيانات على فهم الجدارة الائتمانية للأشخاص
of people like Jenipher, a small-business owner in Nairobi, Kenya.
مثل "جنيفر"، وهي صاحبة أعمال صغيرة في نيروبي، كينيا.
Jenipher is 65 years old, and for decades has been running a food stall
"جنيفر" في الخامسة والستين من العمر، وتعمل في كشك الطعام منذ عقود
in the central business district.
في منطقة الأعمال المركزية.
She has three sons who she put through vocational school,
لديها ثلاثة أبناء والتي قامت بتسجيلهم في مدرسة مهنية،
and she's also the leader of her local chama,
وهي أيضاً زعيمة لحزب "التشاما" المحلي،
or savings group.
أو مجموعات الإدخار.
Jenipher's food stall does well.
يعمل كشك "جنيفر" للطعام بشكل جيد،
She makes just enough every day to cover her expenses.
وتجمع ما يكفي من المال لتغطية نفقاتها كل يوم.
But she's not financially secure.
ولكنها غير آمنه من الناحية المالية.
Any emergency could force her into debt.
ويمكن أن يجبرها أي ظرف طارئ على الدين.
And she has no discretionary income
وليس لديها دخل فائض
to improve her family's way of living,
لتقوم بتحسين ظروف معيشة عائلتها،
for emergencies,
أو لحالات الطوارئ،
or for investing into growing her business.
أو للاستثمار في تنمية مشروعها التجاري.
If Jenipher wants credit, her options are limited.
إن خيارات "جنيفر" محدودة في حال أرادت قرض،
She could get a microloan,
يمكنها الحصول على قرض صغير،
but she'd have to form a group that could help vouch for her credibility.
لكنها ستحتاج حينها لتشكيل مجموعة لتساعد في الشهادة على مصداقيتها.
And even then, the loan sizes would be way too small
ومع ذلك، فستكون أحجام القروض صغيرة جداً
to really have an impact on her business,
وبالتالي لن يكون لها أي تأثير على مشروعها،
averaging around 150 dollars.
بمتوسط دخل وقدره ١٥٠ دولار.
Loan sharks are always an option,
حيتان القروض خيار متاح دائماً،
but with interest rates that are well above 300 percent,
لكن مع أسعار فائدة تتخطى ٣٠٠ في المئة،
they're financially risky.
فانهم يعتبروا في مخاطرة مالية.
And because Jenipher doesn't have collateral or a credit history,
ولأن "جنيفر" لا تملك ضمانات أو سجل ائتماني،
she can't walk into a bank and ask for a business loan.
فإنها لا تستطيع الذهاب وطلب قرض من البنك.
But one day,
ولكن في يوم ما،
Jenipher's son convinced her to download our application
أقنعها إبنها بتثبيت برنامجنا على هاتفها،
and apply for a loan.
وتقديم طلب للحصول على قرض.
Jenipher answered a few questions on her phone
جاوبت "جنيفر" على عدد قليل من الأسئلة من خلال هاتفها
and she gave us access to a few key data points on her device.
وسمحت لنا بالكشف عن بعض المعلومات المهمة في هاتفها.
And here's what we saw.
وهذا ما وجدناه،
So, bad news first.
الأخبار السيئة أولاً.
Jenipher had a low savings balance and no previous loan history.
لدى "جنيفر" ميزانية ادخار منخفضة وليس لها تاريخ قروض سابقة.
These are factors
وهذه العوامل وحدها
that would have thrown up a red flag to a traditional bank.
كافية لرفض القرض من قبل البنوك التقليدية.
But there were other points in her history that showed us
ولكن كانت هناك بعض المعلومات المهمة والتي اظهرت لنا
a much richer picture of her potential.
صورة حسنة وغنية عن إمكانياتها.
So for one,
ومنها،
we saw that she made regular phone calls to her family in Uganda.
رأينا أنها قامت وبشكل منتظم بإجراء المكالمات الهاتفية مع عائلتها في أوغندا.
Well, it turns out that the data shows
أوضحت المعلومات
a four percent increase in repayment
زيادة وقدرها أربعة في المئة من احتمالية السداد
among people who consistently communicate with a few close contacts.
من بين من يقومون وعلى شكل منتظم بإجراء المكالمات الهاتفية مع المقربين.
We could also see
ونستطيع أيضاً أن نرى
that though she traveled around a lot throughout the day,
مع أنها تقوم بالتجول المستمر خلال اليوم.
she actually had pretty regular travel patterns,
فان أنماط تنقلها منتظمة،
and she was either at home or at her food stall.
فكانت إما في المنزل أو في كشك الطعام.
And the data shows a six percent increase in repayment
أوضحت المعلومات زيادة وقدرها ستة في المئة من احتمالية السداد
among customers who are consistent
من بين العملاء المنتظمين
with where they spend most of their time.
في أماكن وجودهم معظم الوقت.
We could also see that she communicated a lot
ورأينا أيضاً بأنها تواصلت كثيراً
with many different people throughout the day
مع العديد من الأشخاص خلال اليوم
and that she had a strong support network.
وأن لديها شبكة دعم قوية من الحلفاء.
Our data shows
تظهر بياناتنا
that people who communicate with more than 58 different contacts
أن الأشخاص الذين يتجاوز تواصلهم مع أكثر من ٥٨ شخصاً
tend to be more likely to be good borrowers.
هم وعلى الأرجح مقترضون جيدون.
In Jenipher's case,
في حالة "جنيفر"
she communicated with 89 different individuals,
تواصلت مع ٨٩ شخصاً
which showed a nine percent increase in her repayment.
مما أوضح زيادة وقدرها تسعة في المئة من احتمالية السداد
These are just some of the thousands of different data points
وهذا فقط عدد قليل من آلاف النقاط المختلفة
that we look at to understand a person's creditworthiness.
والتي نقوم بتحليلها لفهم الأهلية الائتمانية للأفراد.
And after analyzing all of these different data points,
وبعد تحليل جميع هذه النقاط المختلفة،
we took the first risk
أقدمنا على المخاطرة الأولى
and gave Jenipher a loan.
وقدمنا قرض لجنيفر.
This is data that would not be found on a paper trail
لا يمكن رؤية هذا النوع من البيانات في المستندات
or in any formal financial record.
أو حتى في أي من السجلات المالية الرسمية.
But it proves trust.
ومع ذلك أكدت البيانات القدرة على ضمان الثقة.
By looking beyond income,
من خلال النظر الى ما هو أبعد من الدخل
we can see that people in emerging markets
يمكننا أن نرى أن الأشخاص في الأسواق الناشئة
that may seem risky and unpredictable on the surface
والذي يبدو ظاهرهم محفوف بالمخاطر ولا يمكن التنبؤ به
are actually willing and have the capacity to repay.
في الواقع هم على استعداد، ولديهم القدرة على السداد.
Our credit scores have helped us deliver over 200,000 loans in Kenya
ساعدتنا نقاط الأهلية الائتمانية الخاصة بنا على تقديم ٢٠٠.٠٠٠ قرض في كينيا
in just the past year.
خلال السنة الماضية فقط.
And our repayment rates are above 90 percent --
ومعدلات السداد لدينا تفوق نسبة ٩٠ في المئة
which, by the way, is in line with traditional bank repayment rates.
والتي هي بالمناسبة، متماشية مع معدلات السداد في البنوك التقليدية.
With something as simple as a credit score,
من خلال أمر بسيط مثل نقاط الأهلية الائتمانية،
we're giving people the power to build their own futures.
نقوم بإعطاء الناس القدرة على بناء مستقبلهم.
Our customers have used their loans for family expenses,
وقد استخدم عملائنا قروضهم في تغطية المصاريف العائلية،
emergencies, travel
حالات الطوارئ، والسفر
and for investing back into growing their businesses.
والإستثمار مرة أخرى في تنمية أعمالهم.
They're now building better economies and communities
يقومون الآن على بناء أنظمة اقتصادية ومجتمعات أفضل
where more people can succeed.
حيث يمكن للمزيد من الأفراد تحقيق النجاح.
Over the past two years of using our product,
ومن خلال استخدام منتجنا على مدى العامين الماضيين،
Jenipher has increased her savings by 60 percent.
تمكنت "جنيفر" من زيادة مدخراتها بنسبة ٦٠ في المئة.
She's also started two additional food stalls
وأنشأت اثنين أيضاً من أكشاك الطعام الإضافية
and is now making plans for her own restaurant.
وتقوم الآن بالتخطيط من أجل إنشاء مطعمها الخاص.
She's applying for a small-business loan from a commercial bank,
وهي تتقدم للحصول على قرض الأعمال الصغيرة من أحد البنوك التجارية،
because she now has the credit history to prove she deserves it.
لأنه قد أصبح لديها الآن التاريخ الائتماني اللازم لإثبات قدرتها المالية على السداد.
I saw Jenipher in Nairobi just last week,
رأيت "جنيفر" في نيروبي الأسبوع الماضي،
and she told me how excited she was to get started.
وقالت لي كم كانت متحمسة للبدء.
She said,
وقالت حينها،
"Only my son believed I could do this. I didn't think this was for me."
"ولدي فقط هو من أعتقد أنني قادرة على النجاح اذ لم أعتقد ان الأمر يصلح لي"
She's lived her whole life
كانت تعيش طوال حياتها
believing that there was a part of the world that was closed off to her.
وهي تعتقد أن جزءاً من العالم لم يكن متاحا لها
Our job now is to open the world to Jenipher
مهمتنا الآن هي فتح العالم أمام "جنيفر"
and the billions like her that deserve to be trusted.
وأمام المليارات من أمثال "جنيفر" والذين يستحقون الثقة.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)